<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jesus Christ, the same to day, as yesterday, in life and power, in afflictions and sufferings: and the seed of the serpent the same now, as ever, in darkness and emnity; in rage and persecution. Being for removal of the stumbling block out of the way of the simple, concerning the testimony now given against the priests, and their worships, (viz.) Cannot you let them alone, why do ye disturb them, and their assemblies? go unto their houses, or to some private place, and speak to them there; cannot you give the same liberty to others, which you would have yourselves? Wherein is manifested, that what estimation, and enterrainment [sic] the witness of Jesus receiveth at this day from the men of the world, is the same, as it hath alwayes been from the beginning. / Given forth for the sake of the honest-hearted, and in witness of the truth, as it is in Jesus, every where spoken against, scorned, and persecuted, under the reproachful name of quaking. George Bishop.</title>
            <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E861_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206652</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865768</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865768</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E861[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jesus Christ, the same to day, as yesterday, in life and power, in afflictions and sufferings: and the seed of the serpent the same now, as ever, in darkness and emnity; in rage and persecution. Being for removal of the stumbling block out of the way of the simple, concerning the testimony now given against the priests, and their worships, (viz.) Cannot you let them alone, why do ye disturb them, and their assemblies? go unto their houses, or to some private place, and speak to them there; cannot you give the same liberty to others, which you would have yourselves? Wherein is manifested, that what estimation, and enterrainment [sic] the witness of Jesus receiveth at this day from the men of the world, is the same, as it hath alwayes been from the beginning. / Given forth for the sake of the honest-hearted, and in witness of the truth, as it is in Jesus, every where spoken against, scorned, and persecuted, under the reproachful name of quaking. George Bishop.</title>
                  <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 [i.e. 29], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread Eagle at the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 29 misnumbered 28.</note>
                  <note>In the British Library copy the last leaf bears errata identical to those found on D3v (signed D4v), but with a heading "Friends, by reason of the authors absence; .." in place of "Errata"; it may have been intended as a slip cancel. This final leaf is included in the reported pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "quack of Bristoll" follows the words "George Bishop" at end of title; "Decemb: 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Person and offices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118019:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118019:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>JESUS CHRIST,</hi> The ſame to day, as yeſterday, in Life and Power, in Afflictions and Sufferings: And the Seed of the Serpent the ſame now, as ever, in Darkneſs and Emnity; in Rage and Perſecution. <hi>BEING</hi> For Removal of the ſtumbling Block out of the way of the Simple, concerning the Teſtimony now given againſt the Prieſts, and their Worſhips, <hi>(viz.) Cannot you let them alone, why do ye diſturb them, and their Aſſemblies? go unto their houſes, or to ſome private place, and ſpeak to them there; Cannot you give the ſame Liberty to others, which you would have your ſelves? WHEREIN</hi> Is manifeſted, that what Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and Enterrainment the Witneſs of Jeſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth at this day from the men of the World, is the ſame, as it hath alwayes been from the Beginning. <hi>GIVEN FORTH</hi> For the ſake of the honeſt-hearted, and in Witneſs of the Truth, as it is in Jeſus, every where ſpoken againſt, ſcorned, and perſecuted; under the Reproachful Name of Quaking. <hi>GEORGE BISHOP</hi>—</p>
            <q>
               <hi>But as then he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even ſo it is now,</hi> 
               <bibl>Gal. 4. 29.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>And ſhall ſay, Caſt ye up, caſt ye up, prepare the way, take up the ſtumbling Block out of the way of my People,</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſa. 57. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>For ye Brethren became followers of the Churches of God, which in</hi> Judea <hi>are in Chriſt Jeſus; for ye alſo have ſuffered like things of your own Countrey-men, even as they have of the Jews, who both killed the Lord Jeſus, and their own Prophets, and have perſecuted us, and they pleaſe not God, and are contrary to all men: Forbidding us to ſpeak to the Gentiles, that they might be ſaved, to fill up their ſins alway, for the wrath is come upon them to the uttermoſt,</hi> 
               <bibl>1 Theſ. 2. 14. 15, 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black-ſpread Eagle at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:118019:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118019:2"/>
            <head>JESVS CHRIST, The ſame to day, as yeſterday, in Life, and Power, in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and ſufferings; And the Seed of the Serpent the ſame now, as ever, in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Enmity, in Rage and Perſecution.</head>
            <p>VVHereas it is ſaid concerning the Teſtimony now born againſt the Prieſts, <hi>Cannot you let them alone, and their Worſhips? why do ye diſturb them, and their Aſſemblies? go unto their houſes, or to ſome private place, and ſpeak to them there: Cannot you give the ſame Liberty to others, which you have your ſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſay: Our Own, and the Will, and Wiſdome, and time of Man, which ſaith, We will go here, and there, and do, and forbear this, and that, we deny: Did that Spirit rule, it would ſay, Be it far from thee, Let theſe Prieſts, and their Aſſemblies alone; none of thoſe Beatings, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, Reproaches, Impriſonments, taking from Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and Relations, and from wayes of maintainance, whippings, drawings of thy blood, and hazards of thy life ſhall be unto thee.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118019:3"/>
            <p>And we deny the making of diſturbance on our Part, and the Principle from whence it proceedeth, unleſs the ſpeaking of the Word of the Lord be a diſturbance, as it was always accounted even the troubling of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> For our Backs are turned to the Smiters, and our Cheekes to the Nippers, and the Pullers off the Hair, and to him that ſtriketh on one Cheek, the other is turned; neither do we reſiſt Evill with Evill: For, the Principle of Light which we witneſs, in meaſure, leadeth us out of warres, ſtrife, envy, debates, or doing Evill to any, or rendring Evill for Evil; but being curſed, to bleſs; being perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to pray, that their ſins may be forgiven; and is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous that none ſhould periſh, but that all might come to the knowledge of the Truth; and Vengeance we leave to the Lord, whoſe it is, and who will repay it.</p>
            <p>Nor do we deny the ſame liberty to others, which we ought to have; For whatſoever we would that men ſhould do unto us, the ſame we do unto them, according to the Royal Law; and for this purpoſe do we meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and wait upon the Lord our Teacher, to receive his Word and Teſtimony, whether for Inſtruction, or Reproof; and, in our meaſures, we know his Voice from a Strangers, and can try the ſpirits: and even thoſe who oppoſe themſelves have, and may come into our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies freely, and ſpeak, whom we judge in the ſpirit of Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Spiritual man that judgeth all things, and yet he himſelf is judged of no man, whoſe Weapons we make uſe of, which are ſpiritual; not in the fleſh, or the ſpirit of this World, or with the weapons thereof, ſuch as are Beatings, Strikings, Tumults, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, ſhedding of blood, calling to, and before Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and ſuch like; Though out of our Meetings, have ſome of our Friends have drawn and impriſoned, and others have been diſturbed and abuſed.</p>
            <p>And this we further Declare, That what is fallen upon this Generation, and is ſet before their Eyes, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118019:3"/> againſt them, is no new thing, but what hath been witneſſed throughout all Generations, and of which the Scriptures bear Record: For, ſince <hi>Adam</hi> fell into the Tranſgreſſion, to this very day, God hath not left himſelf without a Witneſs; but in all times, by Him who is the Rock of Ages, hath he teſtified againſt the ſinful and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous Generation, and the worſhips and ways there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; Againſt the Sacrifice of <hi>Cain,</hi> by <hi>Abel;</hi> Againſt the Old World, by <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah;</hi> Againſt <hi>Sodom,</hi> by <hi>Lot;</hi> Againſt the People of that time, by <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> Againſt <hi>Egypt,</hi> by <hi>Moſes;</hi> Againſt all the Nations, by the Nation of the Jewes, who had the Law and the Teſtimony; Againſt the Idolatrous Worſhips and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the Kings, Princes, Prieſts, Prophets, and People of the Jews, by his ſervants the Prophets, whom he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to riſe up early, and ſending them, who teſtified even to their faces in the time of their Idolatrous Worſhips and Sacrifices: When the Word was made fleſh, he cleanſed the Temple, ſcourged out thereof the ſheep and the Oxen, poured out the Changers money, overthrew the Tables, ſaid unto thoſe who ſold Doves, <hi>Take ye theſe things hence, make not my Fathers houſe a place of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize;</hi> And in the Temple he diſputed and reaſoned with the Doctors, and teſtified againſt the Traditions and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of the Scribes and Phariſes, the painted Sepulchers, the Graves that appeared not; Againſt them that held up the Figure, when Chriſt the ſubſtance thereof was come, by the Diſciples and Apoſtles, who having receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Power from on high, witneſſed Jeſus who was dead, and roſe again, and aſcended to be the Lord of Glory, and that there was Salvation in no other; and againſt the Temple, and the ſervices thereof, did they teſtifie, even in the Temple, and the Synagogues, in the time of their Worſhips, and alſo againſt the Idol-Gods, and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the Heathens; And ſince the Apoſtles times, to this day, throughout all the Apoſtacy hath he witneſſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118019:4"/> by ſome, or other, to this or that Branch of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, againſt the ſeduced World, and Antichriſts.</p>
            <p>Now as the Spirit of God, in all Ages, carryed forth his ſervants to teſtifie for him who is the Rock of Ages, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the world, and wayes, and worſhips, and Cuſtomes thereof: And as the Prophets ſpake the Word of the Lord againſt the Altars, and their Prieſts, and Prophets, in the preſence of the Kings, and Princes, and People, in the time of their Sacrifices; And as the unchangable Prieſt in the Apoſtles, and Diſciples, witneſſed againſt the Changeable Prieſthood, the whole body of the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Services, and Worſhips, in the Temple, and the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, in the times thereof; And as during the Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the like Witneſs hath been born by ſome, or other, to this day: So now, the true Miniſtry and Teacher being come to be witneſſed, and the worſhip which is in Spirit and Life, and the Witneſs of God raiſed from the Dead in Thouſands, after theſe many Hundred years of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy; It carryes forth in the Power, and at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lord many of his Sonnes and Daughters in whom it is born up, to bear Witneſs againſt the falſe Miniſtry, Prieſts, and Worſhips, even in the times thereof, and to the faces of the Prieſts, and in the preſence of the Rulers: And woe be unto them, if (upon any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultings with fleſh and blood,) they therein diſobey the Commandement of the Lord. For the <note n="a" place="margin">Amos 3. 8.</note> Lyon hath roared, who will not fear? The Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but propheſie? God hath given the <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 68. 11.</note> word, and great are the Company of them that publiſh it: He that can receive it, let him receive it.</p>
            <p>Should not <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 5. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> have gone in to <hi>Pharoah,</hi> when the Lord commanded him; and ſay, Thus ſaith the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Let my People go that they may hold a Feaſt to me in the Wilderneſs?</p>
            <p>Should not the <note n="d" place="margin">1 King. 13. 12, &amp;c.</note> Man of God that came from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> to propheſie againſt the Altar of <hi>Bethel,</hi> have cryed out againſt the Altar in the Word of the Lord, and have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118019:4"/> ſaid, O Altar, Altar, thus ſaith the Lord, Behold, a Child ſhall be born unto the houſe of <hi>David, Joſiah</hi> by name, and upon thee ſhall he offer the Prieſts of the High Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that burn Incenſe upon thee, and mens bones ſhall he burn upon thee; becauſe King <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſtood by it to offer Incenſe, and becauſe it was in the time of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, which were offered by his Command, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and People, and Prieſts thereof were preſent: Should he have gone privately to the Court with Cap and Knee? and have ſpoken gently to the Prieſts, and by a many of <hi>May it pleaſe your Majeſty,</hi> and other flattering Titles, have whiſpered the King in the Ear, or the Prieſts; or applyed to ſome Courtiers, ſo to do; inſtead of coming ſo boldly to diſturb their Worſhips, to affront the King, and his Princes, to their faces, and to weaken the hands of the people, in telling them they ſhould be brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of the King of <hi>Judah</hi> their Enemy, by his Sword, who ſhould offer mens bones, and the bones of the Prieſts, upon the Altar, as ſuch a thing would be now accounted? Should he have gone to <hi>Jeroboams</hi> houſe to have refreſhed himſelf, and to have a reward, at the deſire of the King, after he had prayed, and the Lord had reſtored to him his Arm which was withered, when he had ſtretched it forth againſt the Prophet, and ſaid, <hi>Lay hold on him:</hi> was he not neither to eat bread, nor drink ter in the place, nor to return by the way he came?</p>
            <p>Should not the Prophet <note n="e" place="margin">1 King. 18. 1, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Elijah</hi> have gone at the Word of the Lord, and have ſhewn himſelf to <hi>Ahab,</hi> who had cut off the Prophets of the Lord, ſo that he onely remained; and by reaſon of the great dealth, for want of Rain, had ſent to all Nations to ſeek him; and where he was not found, took an Oath of that Kingdome and Nation, that they found him not? And when <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Art thou he that troubleth Iſrael?</hi> Should he not have anſwered the King; <hi>I have not troubled Iſrael, but thou, and thy Fathers houſe, for that ye have forſaken the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118019:5"/> Commandements of the Lord, and thou haſt ſerved Baalim. Now, therefore, ſend and gather unto me all Iſrael unto Mount Carmel, and the Prophets of Baal 450, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the Grove 400, which eat at Jezabels Table;</hi> And being there gathered together, ſhould he not then have ſaid to them all; <hi>How long halt ye between two Opinions? If the Lord be God, follow him; and if Baal then follow him, put on the Bullock on the Altar, and let the God which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth by Fire, be God.</hi> Should not the Prophets of the Lord, during the times of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> have ſpoken the Word of the Lord to them, and to the falſe Prophets, and Prieſts, and People, againſt their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, and wickedneſses, though it was to the cutting of them off, both Kings, Princes, Prieſts, Prophets, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whether they would hear, or whether they would forbear: Him that dyeth <note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 21. 24.</note> of <hi>Ahab</hi> in the City the Dogs ſhall eat; or he that dyeth in the Field the Fowles of the Air ſhall eat, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Should not <note n="g" place="margin">Jer. 36. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Jeremiah</hi> have wrote another Roll like to the former, which <hi>Jehudi</hi> in the preſence of the Princes and King had cut with a Pen-knife, and thrown in the fire? Should he have been <note n="h" place="margin">Jer. 1. 17, 18.</note> afraid of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? had he not then been confounded before them? was he not made a defenced City, an Iron Pillar, and Brazen Walls againſt the Kings, Princes, Prieſts, and People?</p>
            <p>Should not <note n="i" place="margin">Amos 7. 10. to the end.</note> 
               <hi>Amos</hi> (the Gatherer of Sycamore Fruit) have propheſied again at <hi>Bethel,</hi> becauſe <hi>Amaziah</hi> the Prieſt of <hi>Bethel,</hi> ſent to <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Amos</hi> hath conſpired againſt thee, in the midſt of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Land is not able to bear all his words; for <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith, <hi>Jeroboam ſhall die by the ſword, and Iſrael ſhall ſurely be led away Captive out of their own Land;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>O thou Seer, flee thee away into the Land of Judah, and there eat bread and propheſie there; but propheſie not at Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel: for it is the Kings Chappel, it is the Kings Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should not <note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 3. 7.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> have ſaid to the Phariſees, and Saducers,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118019:5"/> 
               <hi>Ye Generation of Vipers who hath forewarned you to flie from the wrath to come?</hi> Should not <note n="l" place="margin">John 2. 14 15.</note> Chriſt Jeſus in the daies of his fleſh have cleanſed the Temple, and have teſtified againſt the worſhip that was not <note n="m" place="margin">John 4. 23. 24.</note> in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, againſt the Doctors, Lawyers, Scribes, and Phariſees, who were the higheſt Profeſſors, and outwardly moſt religiouſly ſtrict of any in their time? Should not the Apoſtles and Diſciples have gone into the <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 3. 1. to the end, 5. 19. 20, 21.</note> Temple and into the Synagognes, every Sabbath day as their <note n="p" place="margin">10. 17. 14. 18. 4. 19. 26. 19. 8. Acts. 5. 29, 30, 31. Act. 5. 19, 20. 21.</note> manner was, and there have teſtified againſt the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obſervation of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> through the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection<note place="margin">
                  <hi>o</hi> Act. 9. 20. 13. 5. 14, 15. 14. 1. 17. 12.</note> of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, whom they had with wicked hands ſlew and hung upon a Tree; and whom the Lord bad highly exalted, and made Lord and King: and were not the Priſon doores opened by the Angell, and they bad him to go and ſpeak in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all the words of this life? Should not <hi>Stephen,</hi> even before the Councell, have <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 6. 12. 13. 14. 7. 48, 49. 50.</note> ſaid to the high Prieſt, and Phariſees, and People, and teſtified, The moſt High dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not in Temples made with hands; Ye ſtiffenecked, and uncircumciſed in hearts and eares, ye do alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, as your Fathers did, ſo do ye: which of the Prophets have not your Fathers perſecuted, &amp; they have ſlain them that ſhewed before of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Juſt One, of whom ye have been the Betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, &amp; Murtherers, though they had a law that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made himſelf the Son of God, he ſhould die? Should not <hi>Paul</hi> have gon into the <note n="r" place="margin">Acts. 19. 16. 17. 16. to the end, 17. 17.</note> Schools, and on <hi>Mars-Hill,</hi> and in the Market place, and have diſputed againſt the Idol Gods? Should not the Martyrs have teſtified againſt the Prieſts, and Idolatrous Maſſe in the times thereof, though they knew therefore they ſhould be murthered with Torments? Should not the Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Formall worſhips in this and their later gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations have been witneſſed againſt, though guarded by lawes, and fortified with the powers of theſe Nations? Was not the Dread of the Lord upon his witneſſes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118019:6"/> aforementioned, and neceſſity laid upon them ſo to do? Conſulted they with any other Oracle? Had not woe been to them, ſhould they have been diſobedient? Are theſe things new, are theſe things ſtrange? Again, were not the witneſſes of God in their Generations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of as ſcornfully and baſely as they are at this day, and the Word of the Lord, which they ſpake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and ſleighted as it is now? received they any other, or better entertainment of the Generations, to whom they ſpake, and againſt whom they teſtified, from the beginning? Mind and conſider.</p>
            <p>He that lived in the dayes of <note n="s" place="margin">Gen. 4. 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Abel</hi> might have ſeen <hi>Cain</hi> hating his Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe his Sacrifice was accepted: And though God witneſſed it to <hi>Cain,</hi> and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of <hi>Abels</hi> Gifts, and reaſoned with him: If thou doeſt well, ſhalt thou not be accepted. if thou doeſt evill ſin lies at the doore; Yet, he lifted up his hand and ſlew him. He that lived in the dayes of <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 6. 7. chap. 2 Pet. 2. 5. 1 Pet. 3. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> might have ſeen how that world ſlighted his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and how ridiculous was his propheſying of a Flood accounted, and the making of an Ark to ſwim upon the dry Land? Thoſe who lived in the dayes of <hi>Lot</hi> might have heard the men of <hi>Sodom</hi> ſay, This <note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 19. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> Fellow came in to Sojourn, and he will needs be a Judge, when he ſaid to them; Nay, my Brethren do not ſo wickedly, upon their calling on him to bring out the ſtrangers that they might know them, &amp; how he ſeemed to his Sons in Law, as one that <note n="w" place="margin">Gen. 19. 14.</note> mocked, when he told them, The Lord would deſtroy that City. <note n="x" place="margin">Exod. 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> who is the Lord that I ſhould obey his Voice, to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, I know not the Lord, nor will I let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go; Ye are Idle, ye are Idle, wherefore do ye <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> let the People from their works? get you unto your bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. Did not <note n="y" place="margin">1 King. 13. 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſtretch forth his hand, and ſay, Lay hold on him, by the Man of God that propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Altar, and though his Arme was reſtored,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118019:6"/> and the ſign came preſently to paſſe which he gave: to wit, the Altar rent and the aſhes poured out, as the Man of God ſaid? and at his prayer, did he, or <hi>Iſrael</hi> believe the Word or the Lord, ſpoken by him, to turn from their evill wayes, that the Judgments threatned might not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them? Did <note n="z" place="margin">1 King. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab</hi> forſake <hi>Baal,</hi> or the people his worſhip, though he <note n="a" place="margin">24.</note> could not anſwer by fire, and though they <note n="b" place="margin">29.</note> ſaid, it was well ſaid, That the God that anſwered by fire ſhould be God; And <note n="c" place="margin">40.</note> ſlew all the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> becauſe the Lord whom <hi>Elijah</hi> prayed to, anſwered by fire, and though afterwards at his prayer, they that day had <note n="d" place="margin">45.</note> abundance of Rain, which for <note n="e" place="margin">Jam. 5. 17. 18.</note> three yeares and ſix months before was ſhut up; Was not <hi>Elijah</hi> the very next <note n="f" place="margin">1 King. 19. 2 3.</note> day conſtrained to flie for his life? <note n="g" place="margin">1 King. 21. 25.</note> was there any like <hi>Ahab</hi> who ſold himſelf to commit Iniquity, though the Hand of the Lord appeared more in his daies, then any of his Succeſſors againſt <hi>Syria,</hi> and in mighty wonders, through his word by his Prophets? Said not <note n="h" place="margin">1 King. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab</hi> of <hi>Micajah,</hi> This man propheſies no good of mee but evill. Thus ſaith the King take <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cajah,</hi> and carry him back to <hi>Hamon</hi> the Governour of the Citie, and to <hi>Joaſh</hi> the Kings Son, and ſay, thus<note n="i" place="margin">26, 27.</note> ſaith the King, put this Fellow into the Priſon, and feed him with Bread of Affliction, and with water of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction untill I come in Peace; And, <note n="k" place="margin">24.</note> which way came the Spirit of the Lord from mee to ſpeak to thee, ſaid <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the Falſe Prophet, the ſame time, when he ſmote <hi>Micajah</hi> on the face. What made this <note n="l" place="margin">2 King. 9. 11.</note> mad fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low with thee, ſaid the Captains of the Hoſt, to Jehu, by the Prophet, when he came and anointed him from the Lord to be King of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Fared it any better with the reſt of the Prophets, whom the Lord <note n="m" place="margin">2 Chro. 36. 15. 16. Jer. 7. 25.—25. 24.—35. 15.—26. 5.—29. 19.—32. 33.—44. 4.</note> riſing Early ſent unto them; ſaying, O do not the <note n="n" place="margin">Jer. 44. 4.</note> Abominable thing that I hate, was the Burthen of the Word of the Lord, any otherwiſe eſteemed? ſaid they not unto the <note n="o" place="margin">Amos. 2. 11,</note> Prophets propheſy not, and gave they not wine to the <hi>Nazarites</hi> to Drink? Anſwered not all the <note n="p" place="margin">Jer. 43. 2.</note> Proud
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118019:7"/> men, thou ſpeakeſt falſely, as for the Word of the <note n="q" place="margin">Jer. 44. 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> Lord that thou haſt ſpoken, in the Name of the Lord, we will not hearken thereunto, but we will certainly do whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thing goeth forth out of our own mouth? Who hath believed our <note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 53. 1.</note> Report, and to whom hath the Arm of the Lord been revealed <note n="s" place="margin">Iſa. 65. 2. Rom. 10. 21.</note>? But to <hi>Iſrael</hi> he ſaith all the day long have I ſtretched forth my hands to a Gain-ſaying, and a Rebellious People; Then I ſaid I have <note n="u" place="margin">Iſa. 49. 4.</note> Laboured in Vain, I have ſpent my ſtrength for nought, I heard the <note n="w" place="margin">Jer. 20. 10.</note> defamings of many, fear on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, Report, ſay they, and we will report it; all my Familiars watched for my haltings ſaying, peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he will be inticed, and we ſhall, prevail againſt him, and we ſhall take our Revenge on him. How were they <hi>x</hi> mocked by every one, and deſpiſed, and the<note place="margin">Jer. 6. 10: 20. 7. 8.</note> Word of the Lord made a reproach unto them, <note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 8. 18.</note> and a deriſion daily and for ſigns and wonders? Then I ſaid I will not <note n="z" place="margin">Jer. 20. 9.</note> make mention of him, nor ſpeak any more in his name, but his Word was in my heart, as burning fire, ſhut up in my bones, and I was weary with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, and I could not ſtay. How was <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 20. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> brought forth walking three years naked, and barefoot? And <note n="b" place="margin">Jer: 13. 4, 5, 9, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Jeremiah</hi> hiding a Girdle in the bank of <hi>Eupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> till it ir was marred; And carrying <note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 25. 51. to the 30.</note> a Cup to all the Nations to drink, that they might drink and be drunken, and be moved, and be mad, and ſpue, and fall, and riſe no more? And <note n="d" place="margin">Ezek. 4. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiel</hi> pourtraying Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem on a Tileſtone, laying ſiedge againſt it, caſting up Mounts and raiſing battring Rams, and ſetting an Iron Pan between him and the City: <note n="e" place="margin">Ezek. 12. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> Digging through a wall in the middle of the day, and bringing out thereof his ſtuffe in the ſight of his People; <note n="f" place="margin">Ezek. 5. 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> Cutting off his hair from his head, and beard, and weighing it in a Balance openly, and caſting one third thereof into the Ayre, and another third burning with fire; And cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another third in pieces with his Knife <note n="g" place="margin">Ezek. 4, 5.</note> Lying 390. daies on his left ſide, and <note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 4. 6.</note> 40. daies on his <note n="i" place="margin">9. 10, 11, 12, 15.</note> Right ſide,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118019:7"/> and during the times aforeſaid, eating his Bread ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Beaſts dung by weight, and drinking his water by meaſure? How ridiculous were theſe things in the Eyes of thoſe Generations, and how were they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as the Actions of <note n="k" place="margin">Jer. 29. 24, 25, 26.</note> Mad-men: How did they caſt them into Priſons, and Dungeons, and the Stocks, as Mad-men, and how were ſome of them put to death? And <note n="l" place="margin">2 Chron. 36. 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> the Lord God of their Fathers ſent to them by his Meſſengers, riſing up betimes, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, becauſe he had compaſſion on his people, and on his dwelling place; but they mocked the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of God, and deſpiſed his Words, and miſuſed his Prophets, untill the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his people, and there was no remedy.</p>
            <p>Was not <hi>John</hi> the <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 11. 11</note> greateſt of Prophets, who came in the <note n="n" place="margin">Luke 1. 17. Matth. 11. 14.</note> Spirit and Power of <hi>Elias,</hi> turning the hearts of the Fathers unto the Children, <note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 3. 2, 3.</note> crying in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths ſtrait:</hi> The Meſſenger that went before his face, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Repent, for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand; the</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Ax is laid to the Root of the Tree. Every Tree that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not forth good fruit is hewen down, and caſt into the fire;</hi> called <note n="r" place="margin">Luke 7. 33.</note> a Devil, though he came neither eating, and drinking but in a Garment of Camels Hair, tyed about with a Leathern Girdle: was he not caſt into priſon, and <note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 14. 3, 10.</note> beheaded?</p>
            <p>When the Son of God, of whom all the <note n="t" place="margin">Luke 1. 70. 24. 27. Act. 3. 18, 21.</note> Prophets ſpake, came himſelf: was he otherwiſe accounted of? was he otherwiſe intreated by thoſe who cryed out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Fathers, for perſecuting and killing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, whoſe Tombes they built, and whoſe Sepulchres they garniſhed: was he <note n="u" place="margin">John 1. 26. 9. 29. 1 Cor. 2. 6, 8. Act. 13. 27.</note> known by his fleſh to that Generation? <note n="w" place="margin">Phil. 2. 7.</note> made he not himſelf of no Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? was not his (<hi>x</hi>) Viſage more marr'd then any mans, of no <note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 53. 2, 3.</note> Comelineſs and Beauty, whereby he ſhould<note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 52. 14.</note> be deſired? Was he not a <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 53. 3.</note> man of ſorrows, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118019:8"/> with griefs, eſteemed as <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 53. 4.</note> ſtricken, and ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of God, and afflicted, deſpiſed, and rejected of men; and were not their faces as it were hid from him? Was he not <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 53. 7.</note> afflicted and oppreſſed, <note n="d" place="margin">John 8. 49. 10. 39. Luke 4. 28, 29, 30.</note> tumulted and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, blind-folded <note n="e" place="margin">Luke 22. 64.</note> and buffetted, ſmote on the Cheek, and <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 27. 30.</note> ſpit upon, <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 27. 29.</note> crowned with Thorns, <note n="h" place="margin">Mark 15. 15</note> and ſcourged, <note n="i" place="margin">Luke 23. 35.</note> derided, <note n="k" place="margin">Mark 15. 29</note> rayled on, and <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 27. 39.</note> and reviled, and <note n="m" place="margin">Luke 18. 32.</note> ſpightfully entreated and mocked, on the Croſs, <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 27. 41.</note> by the chief Prieſts, and a Murderer <note n="o" place="margin">Luke 23. 11</note> deſired be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <note n="p" place="margin">Luke 23. 18, 19, 24, 25.</note> and in his <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 8. 33.</note> Humiliation, was not his Judgment taken away, <note n="r" place="margin">Eſa. 53. 12.</note> numbred amongſt Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and put to death, and his <note n="s" place="margin">Eſa. 53. 9.</note> Grave made with the Wicked? Was he not called a <note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 11. 19.</note> man Gluttonous, and a Wine-bibber, a Friend of Publicans and Sinners, <note n="u" place="margin">Joh. 5. 18. Luke 6. 4. to the 12.</note> a Breaker of the Sabbath, and of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the <note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 15. 2. 3</note> Traditions of the Elders, (<hi>w</hi>) a Mad-man, one <note n="y" place="margin">Mark 3. 21.</note> beſides himſelf, a <note n="z" place="margin">Joh. 8. 48.</note> Samaritan, a <note n="a" place="margin">Mark 3. 23.</note> Devil; yea the <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 9. 34.</note> Prince of Devils; yea, and a <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 26. 65, 66.</note> Blaſphemer, and put to Death as ſuch a One, though he <note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 7. 40.</note> ſpake, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver man ſpake, with <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 7. 29.</note> Authority, and not as the Scribes, though none <note n="f" place="margin">John 8. 46.</note> could convince him of ſinne, <note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 53. 9.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was any deceit found in his mouth; And though mighty <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 2. 22.</note> Signs and Wonders were done by him? <hi>For a</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">John. 10. 33.</note> 
               <hi>good work we ſtone thee not, but for Blaſphemy, that thou being a man makeſt thy ſelf the Son of God. We have</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luke 23. 2.</note> 
               <hi>found this Fellow perverting the Nation, and forbidding Tribute to be given to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying, that himſelf is Chriſt, a King. We have a</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Joh. 19. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Law, that whoſoever ſaith he is the Son of God ſhall die. Ye have heard his</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Matth. 26 64, 65 66. Mark 15. 61, 62, 63, 64.</note> 
               <hi>Blaſphemy, what think ye?</hi> And they all cryed out, <hi>He is worthy of death.</hi> When he ſaid he was the Son of God, upon the High Prieſts adjuring him to tell him, <hi>Whether he was Chriſt the Son of the Bleſſed?</hi> And he ſaid, <hi>I am; and ye ſhall ſee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118019:8"/> the Son of Man ſitting on the right hand of Power, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Clouds of Heaven.</hi> And was not the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles and Diſciples, who witneſſed him, even Jeſus riſen from the Dead, the ſame? were they not <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 22. 19.</note> beaten and <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 21. 30.</note> haled out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 8. 3.</note> and out of every houſe, both men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 16. 20, 22, 35, 36, 38.</note> brought before Magiſtrates, commanded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the <note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 8. 24. Act. 16. 39.</note> Countrey, caſt into <note n="s" place="margin">Act. 5. 18.</note> the common pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and into the <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 16. 24.</note> Stocks, <note n="u" place="margin">Act. 17. 32.</note> mocked and ſcorned, <note n="w" place="margin">Act. 22. 25. 5. 40. 16. 22, 23, 37.</note> ſcourged and (<hi>x</hi>) ſtoned, and <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 14. 5.</note> deſpightfully uſed: were not <note n="r" place="margin">Act. 14. 5. 17. 5, 6, 7.</note> Tumults made upon them, and Uproars, and<note n="p" place="margin">Act. 7. 58, 59. 5. 19.</note> houſes aſſaulted to bring them out to the People? were they not <note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 8. 36.</note> killed all the day long, and accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter, and ſlain with the ſword? Were they not ſet forth as <note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 9. 13.</note> ſpectacles to Men and Angels? accounted as the off-ſcowring of all things, and the filth of the World, <note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 8. Mar. 27. 63.</note> as Deceivers, <note n="w" place="margin">Act. 24. 5.</note> Movers of Sedition, <note n="x" place="margin">Act. 24. 5. 16. 20, 21.</note> turbulent and peſtilent fellows, Mad-men, <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 17. 6.</note> turners of the World up-ſide down, <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 16. 20.</note> Diſturbers of the Peace, <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 16. 11, 13.</note> Blaſphemers of the Law, and of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Holy Place: This Fellow <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 18. 13.</note> perſwadeth men to worſhip God contrary to the Law; <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 17. 7.</note> Enemies to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 21. 28, 29, 30.</note> Polluters of the Holy Place, <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 26. 6.</note> Profaners of the Temple, <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 6. 14.</note> Changers of the Laws and Cuſtoms, <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 21. 28.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned men, <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 28. 22.</note> a Sect every where ſpoken againſt, their <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 17. 18.</note> Doctrine babling, <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 2. 13, 15. to the 22.</note> the Powrings forth of the Spirit as <hi>Joel</hi> had propheſied, a filling with new Wine, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 24. 9.</note> a People hated of all men, as was Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the Captain of their Salvation, who was their Enſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſufferings; who of theſe things fore-told them, and that thoſe that <hi>u</hi> killed them, ſhould think they did God good ſervice, and as were the witneſſes which went before them, who were <note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note> tortured, not accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliverance; who had Tryals of Cruel Mockings, and Scourgings, of Bonds and Impriſonments, who were ſtoned, and ſawn aſunder, and tempted and ſlain with the<note n="o" place="margin">Joh. 16. 2.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118019:9"/> ſword, and who wandered about in Sheepskins, and Goat-skins, in Deſerts, and on Mountains, in Dens and Caves of the earth, being deſtitute, afflicted, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, of whom the world was not worthy: wherefore God prepared for them a City, and is not aſhamed to be called their Father.</p>
            <p>And ſince their times have not the witneſſes of God throughout the Apoſtacy to this day taſted, endured, and gone through the ſame ſufferings, and their teſtimony after the ſame manner accounted of and deſpiſed, in which to be particular, would fill a volume; and of which this very Generation doth not want many preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and living Teſtimonies?</p>
            <p>And theſe things received not <hi>Abel</hi> from his Brother <hi>Cain? Lot</hi> from the men of <hi>Sodom,</hi> whom whileſt he was amongſt, were preſerved for his ſake; and from his ſons in Lawes, whom he ſought to preſerve? And <hi>Iſaac</hi> from the ſonne of <hi>Hagar</hi> the Egyptian: And the Prophets of the Lord, from the Kings, Princes, falſe Prophets, Prieſts, and people of Iſrael and Judah: And the Meſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, the ſon of God, from the Nation of the Jews, the High-Prieſts, Lawyers, Scribes and Phariſees, amongſt whom he came, according to all the Prophecies: And the Apoſtles and Diſciples from their own Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and from thoſe who were called the devout, and honourable, and were moſt ſtrict in the profeſsion of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which was once commanded of God.</p>
            <p>And the ſubſtance from thoſe who held the ſhadow: the Jew inwardly, from the Jew outwardly: the life from thoſe who ſtood for the letter: the heavenly things from thoſe who were for the Pattern: the Circumciſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, from the Circumciſion made with hands: the Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> from the Prieſts after the order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Prophet whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid the Lord their God ſhould rayſe up like unto him, whom whoſoever did not hear, ſhould be cut off from his people, from thoſe who profeſſed the Law of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118019:9"/> 
               <hi>Moſes.</hi> The ſeed when it came, untill which came, the Law was added becauſe of Tranſgreſsion, by thoſe who were in the obſervation of the Law. And the Martyrs and witneſſes of Jeſus to this day, from the Chiefe in the profeſsion of Religion.</p>
            <p>And of the ſame Cup do we drink, and the ſame Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure do we receive, who come to witneſs the ſame life made manifeſt in us, from this adulterous Generation; yea, even from thoſe who in profeſsion exceed any who have been in the world, as they do in perſecution, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their power, who condemning thoſe in words, who perſecuted and killed the Prophets, and Jeſus, and the Apoſtles, and the Martyrs, &amp;c. do themſelves perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute us now, who not long ſince were perſecuted with them; and being under the ſame condemnation, were ſought to be cut off, and (having loſt the ſavour they once had) become one with thoſe in our perſecution, who formerly ſo perſecuted them &amp; us, (a crime of which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages have not been guilty) for that we witneſs (in our meaſures) the life of much of what themſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, as the Apoſtles did the ſubſtance of the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> in the obſervation of which, their perſecuters were ſo blindly zealous, &amp; alſo; the day come, which they have been ſo long expecting, and earneſtly deſiring, though the Scriptures bear Record to us of all theſe things to this Generation, which the Generations in the Prophets dayes had not, nor thoſe in the Apoſtles for much of what they were led into by the ſpirit; and though this Generation pretend to the Scriptures as their Rule and Judge, and tryall of ſpirits, and to the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but are not ſo much as in the letter of things to which they pretend; they who were deſpiſed, deſpiſe, and thoſe who were perſecuted perſecute, though when it was their own caſe, they cryed out againſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</p>
            <p>Thus is Jeſus Chriſt the ſeed of God, the ſame to day as yeſterday in life &amp; power, in afflictions &amp; ſufferings; &amp;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118019:10"/> the Children whom God hath given him out of the world for ſignes and wonders in the ſight of every gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their enemies. And thus is the ſeed of the Serpent the ſame now as ever in darkneſs and enmity, in oppoſition &amp; perſecution; and every Generation of them more blinde and envious, then their Fathers, who now are come to perſecute us for the ſame things practiſed, which themſelves profeſsin the letter. And thus is the eternall ſpirit from which the Prophets ſpake and the Apoſtles, and by which Jeſus Chriſt offered up himſelfe, a Myſtery which from the beginning hath been hid in God, whom thoſe who believed not in the light never knew, nor can know: from that eye it hath been, is, and ever ſhall be ſhut up, even from the wiſe and prudent, who by wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom know not God, who hath created all things by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who is the light of the world, who enlightens every one that commeth into the world.</p>
            <p>He <note n="q" place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 9.</note> preached in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> to the ſpirits in priſon, but that old world neither repented nor believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: He was with the <note n="r" place="margin">Acts 7. 38, 39</note> Church of the Jews in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and with the Angel, who ſpake to <hi>Moſes</hi> in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and with the Fathers who received the lively Oracles, but they would not obey, but thruſt him from them, and in their hearts returned to <hi>Egypt:</hi> He ſpake and teſtified in the Prophets; but they would not hear; they who handled the Law knew him not; and <note n="s" place="margin">Jer. 2. 8.</note> the great things of his Law, which he ſent to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> were<note n="t" place="margin">Hoſ. 8. 12.</note> were accounted as a ſtrange thing: He came in fleſh, yet he was not <note n="v" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 8.</note> known to the Princes of this world, nor his voice, nor <note n="w" place="margin">Acts 13. 27.</note> the voyces of the Prophets, which ſpake of him, though they were read every Sabbath-day. He came in ſpirit and power in the Apoſtles and Diſciples, and there he is <note n="x" place="margin">Acts 13. 45.</note> contradicted and blaſphemed, and <note n="y" place="margin">Acts 3. 13. 14</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed above the meaſure of former Generations, as the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>z</hi> Acts 13. 45.</note> meaſure of the ſpirit in them exceeded: and they judged themſelves unworthy of eternall life.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118019:10"/>
            <p>In his Prophets times who <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 10. 11, 12.</note> were all ignorant, who were all dumb Doggs that could not bark, who were blinde, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber, who were greedy Doggs, who can never have enough, who were Shepheards that could not underſtand, who all looked to their own way, every one for his gain from his quarter, who ſaid, come ye, I will ſetch wine, we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as to day, and much more abundant, but the <hi>Watchmen</hi> of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Who <note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 22. 25</note> conſpired againſt the Lord, and were in the midſt of <hi>Judah,</hi> as a roaring Lyon, ravening the prey, devouring ſouls, taking the Treaſure and pretious things making many Widdows, and ſpeakers of lies in the name of the Lord? to whom was the <note n="c" place="margin">Iſay 29. 9. 10, 11, 12.</note> Viſion of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as a Book ſealed? on whom did the Lord powre out the ſpirit of deep ſlumber, cloſed their eyes, and cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? who were drunken, but not with wine, who did ſtagger, but not with ſtrong drink, to whom was night, and no viſion, and darkneſs that they could not divine? upon whom went the Sun down, and the day became dark? who cauſed the people to erre, and bite with their teeth, and cryed peace, and he that put not into their<note place="margin">
                  <hi>d</hi> Mic. 3. 5. 6.</note> mouthes, they prepare Warre againſt him, who taught for hire, and divined for mony, and yet leaned upon the Lord, and ſaid, Is not the Lord amongſt us? none evill can come upon us, for whoſe ſake <hi>Sion</hi> was plowed as a field, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> became heaps, and the Mountains of the houſe as the high places of the Forreſts; who were confounded, and had their loins covered, for that there was no anſwer from God, but the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Seers,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Diviners,</hi> Whoſe <note n="e" place="margin">Zach. 11. 17</note> right eye was to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly darkened, and whoſe Arm clean dryed up? but the <hi>Idoll Shepheard,</hi> Whoſe ſoul abhorred God, and his ſoul loathed them, who in Companies in the way murthered by conſent, as the Troops of Robbers wait for a man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>f</hi> Hoſ. 6. 9.</note> who violated the Law, and prophaned the holy things, and hid their eyes from the Sabbaths, and put no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118019:11"/> between the clean and the unclean, whoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings<note place="margin">Mal. 2. 2.</note> were curſed, but the <hi>Prieſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the dayes of his fleſh, who kept away the <note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 11. 52.</note> key of knowledge and neither entered into the Kingdom, nor ſuffered others, but the chief Prieſts, Phariſees, Lawyers, Scribes and Doctors, who read him daily to the people? who above all men were outwardly moſt holy, whom he notwithſtanding calls <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 23. 16. 17. 19. 26. 15. 14.</note> blinde Guides, leading the b inde, and both falling into the ditch, though they ſaid to the <note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 7. 47. 48, 49.</note> Officers, Are you alſo deceived, have any of the Rulers, or the Phariſees believed on him, but theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who know not the Law, are accurſed? how high were all their expectations of the Meſſiah, the Prince of his people, and of the powrings forth of his ſpirit in the Prophecies; but when he came, and the Propheſies in him fulfilled, and the ſpirit powred forth, how baſely eſteemed, deſpiſed, rejected, unbelieved, and perſecuted? and the ſame was alſo in the dayes of the Apoſtles. Where the life hath been moſt manifeſted, there that hath been moſt in myſtery, to thoſe who believed not in the light; behold he commeth in Clouds, and the fleſh in which it hath ſo appeared, with the leaſt comlineſs and beauty, whereby it ſhould be deſired, and moſt perſecuted: Who believed in <hi>Jeſus</hi> by ſeeing him in the fleſh, to be the ſon of God? And above all men, as to this world, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were accounted moſt miſerable? For. <note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 27, 28, 29.</note> God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and the weak things to confound the things that are mighty, and the baſe things of the world, and the things that are deſpiſed hath God choſen: yea the things that are not, to bring to naught the things that are, that no fleſh might glory in his preſence, and <note n="l" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 10.</note> that the truth might not be received, but for the love of it.</p>
            <p>When <note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 19. 41. 42, 43, 44.</note> Jeſus came near, he beheld the City, and wept over it, Saying, if thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things that belong to thy peace, but now they are hid from thine eyes; for the dayes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118019:11"/> ſhall come upon thee, that thine enemies ſhall caſt a Trench about thee, and compaſs thee round, and keep thee in on every ſide, and ſhall lay thee, even with the ground, and thy Children within thee; and they ſhall not leave in thee one ſtone upon another, becauſe thou kneweſt not the houre of thy viſitation.</p>
            <p>Friends, <hi>It concerns your pretious ſouls eternally, to know this houre of your viſitation, leaſt you continuing to fall upon the Corner-ſtone the Rock of Ages, and thus to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it, and evilly to requite the dear love of God to you, in raiſing up his witneſs against you, warning you of all deceipt, and directing you where Redemption is to be found, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, it fall upon you, and grinde you to powder. For, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the Kingdom of God is come amongſt you, the Son is come to the Vineyard, to look for fruit, and upon ſuch dayes of the Son of man are you fallen, that you are not aware of, whom if you ſhall ſtill conſult againſt, caſt out, and murther, and call the ſpirit of judgement and of burning, of the Devill, whereby the filth of the Daughter of Sion is purged away, and which makes the earth to ſhake, and the Pillars of the houſe to tremble, and the ſtrong man to bow, and the mighty man to cry bitterly, he will</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 20. 13. 14, 15, 16. Mat. 21. 41.</note> 
               <hi>miſerably deſtroy you, and let out the Vineyard unto others, and ſad will be your portion; for all ſins ſhall be forgiven unto the ſons of men and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, wherewith ſoever they ſhall blaſpheme; but he that</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>o</hi> Mark 3. 28. 29, 30.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall blaſpheme againſt the Holy Ghoſt, hath never forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but is in danger of eternall damnation: This ſaid Chriſt, becauſe they ſaid, He had an unclean ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sink down therefore, to that of God in every one of your Conſciences, the light of Ieſus Chriſt, wherewith he lightens every one that commeth into the world, the faithfull and true witneſs, to which we ſpeak; And let us reaſon a little together, what is that about which you ſo much contend, and for which you have drawn, and are drawing, and ready to draw, the blood of thoſe, who
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118019:12"/> longing for the Redemption of the ſeed in every one of you, which lies, and is ſought to be held in Captivity by the Prieſts, and their worſhips, and knowing whom you reſiſt, and the terrors of the Lord are made to teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wayes you walk in, as leading to hell, and as tending to the Chambers of death; and to ſhew you, would you hear, the way that leads to eternall life, whoſe Bowels, even when under ſufferings by you, for ſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing, and againſt the ſpirit that rules in you, earn after you, and the ſalvation of your ſouls, which are pretious, God is their witneſs?</p>
            <p>Are they Churches of Chriſt? ſearch and ſee in the Scriptures, which you ſay is your Rule, there all might <note n="p" place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 31</note> propheſie, one by one, and when any thing was <note n="q" place="margin">30.</note> reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to another that ſate by, the firſt held his peace, and the <note n="r" place="margin">29.</note> Prophets, two or three might ſpeak, and the reſt judge there was the <note n="s" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 15.</note> ſpirituall man, who judgeth all things, and yet he himſelfe is judged of no man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note n="t" place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 25.</note> meekneſs were inſtructed, thoſe that oppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. There, <note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 24. 25.</note> the unbeliever and unlearned by found Doctrine was convinced of all, and judged of all; and ſecrets of his heart made manifeſt, ſo that falling down on his face, he worſhipped God, and reported, God is in you of a truth. There were no ſtrikings, nor quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, nor Tumults, nor drawings of blood, nor calling to, or haling before Magiſtrates, or carrying to priſons, whippings, ſtockings, throwing into Dungeons, and keeping cloſe priſoners from friends, and maintenance, for ſpeaking or oppoſing; nor ſending ſuch to their homes from Tithing to Tithing, who came to viſit them, never were they found perſecuting, but were alwayes after this manner intreated, and perſecuted: who ever perſecuted was out of the Doctrine of Chriſt. The <note n="w" place="margin">1 Theſ. 1. 1.</note> Church is in God, the <note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 15.</note> Pillar and Ground of Truth, <note n="y" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 4, 5.</note> liveing ſtones, built a ſpirituall houſe upon the living Stone. Are yours ſuch, are theſe things found amongſt you? Be coole, and conſider, for theſe things are plain, he that runs may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118019:12"/> read them: be not alwayes deceived; by their fruits, you may know them to be the <note n="a" place="margin">Rev, 2. 9. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Synagogues</hi> of Satan, the <note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 18. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Cages</hi> of every unclean and hateful Bird, the <hi>Haitation</hi> of <hi>Devills,</hi> and the hold of every foul ſpirit: plain deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you will finde at length to be beſt. Are the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Harlots, Drunkards, Enviers, Swearers, Lyars, Hypocrites, Cheaters, Strikers, &amp;c. the Members of Chriſt? are ſuch the Piller and Ground of Truth? are thoſe who are dead in Treſpaſſes and ſins, living ſtones built upon the living foundation? Is ſtriking, tumulting, and ſuch like, in meekneſs inſtructing thoſe who oppoſe or convincing the unbeliever, and unlearned, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting the ſecrets of his heart? what Churches are they, when ſuch things as theſe are found? where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Teſtimony of the Lord will be endured, nor an unbeliever, and unlearned ſo accounted, either convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, or permitted to ſtay there ſo to be?</p>
            <p>Are your Prieſts, Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt? ſearch and ſee: they were <note n="c" place="margin">Tit. 1. 7.</note> blameleſs, as the Stewards of God, not ſelf-willed, nor ſoon angry, nor given to wine, nor to filthy lucre, no ſtrikers, nor <note n="†" place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 3.</note> ſtrivers, nor brawlers, nor envious, nor raylers, nor covetous, <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 56. 11.</note> nor ſeeking their gain from their Quarters, <note n="e" place="margin">Mic. 3. 5. 6, 7. 1 Tim. 12. 24.</note> nor Biters with their teeth, nor preparers of warre, where it is not put into their mouths, nor receivers of Tithes, Oblations, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, &amp;c. or ſuers for treble dammages, or caſters into priſon, of thoſe who refuſe, for whom they neither plant nor plow, nor ſowe; nor makers of <note n="f" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 3.</note> Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of the people, through covetouſneſs with feigned words, or having <note n="g" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 14.</note> hearts exerciſed with covetous prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices: they were not called of men, <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 23, 10.</note> Maſters, nor <note n="i" place="margin">Luke 11. 43 Mat. 23. 6. 7, 8</note> ſtood praying in the Synagogues, or for a pretence made long Prayers, nor loved the uppermoſt ſeats in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and at Feaſts, nor greeting in the Market place, <note n="k" place="margin">Mich. 3. 11</note> nor preached for hire, nor divined for mony, nor had or ſought for approbation of men, or a State-maintenance, or a ſtate conſiſtory; nor ſpake <note n="l" place="margin">Jer: 14: 4: 9. 14:</note> a lying Divination, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118019:13"/> imagination of their own heart for the word of the Lord; nor came with <note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 4.</note> the entiſing words of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor by <note n="n" place="margin">Gal. 1. 1. 11.</note> or in the will, and time of man, nor <note n="o" place="margin">Jer. 13. 21.</note> ran when they were not ſent, nor made the <note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 9. 12. 13, 14.</note> Goſpel bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome, nor had they any <note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 11.</note> certain dwelling place, nor did they perſecute, nor called they to Magiſtrates, nor haled to priſon, thoſe who ſpoke to them in the name of the Lord, or oppoſed: nor had <note n="†" place="margin">Jud. 16.</note> mens perſons, in admiration for advantage; nor were <note n="*" place="margin">James 2. 1. to 13.</note> reſpecters of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But <note n="r" place="margin">Tit. 1. 8.</note> were lovers of Hoſpitality, lovers of good men, ſober, juſt, holy, temperate, holding forth the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full word, by ſound Doctrine, exhorting and convincing gain-ſayers, <note n="s" place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 24.</note> gentle to all men, apt to teach, patient, in meekneſs inſtructing them that oppoſe, <note n="t" place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 2.</note> commending what they ſaid unto every mans Conſcience in the ſight of God, even to thoſe that oppoſed themſelves, <note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 1. 1. 12.</note> receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel not by man, nor the will of man, nor were they raught it, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt in them. In all <note n="w" place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 4. to the 11th.</note> things approving of themſelves, as the Miniſters of God, in much patience, in afflictions, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes, in ſtripes, in impriſonments, in Tumults, in Labours, in watchings, in faſtings; by pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by knowledge, by long-ſuffering, by kindneſs, by the Holy-Ghoſt, by love unfeigned, by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the Armour of righteouſneſs on the right hand, and on the left; by honour and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by evill report, and good report: as deceivers, and yet true, as unknown, and yet well known; as dying, and yet behold they lived; as chaſtened, and yet not killed; as ſorrowful, yet alwayes rejoycing; as poor, yet making many rich; as having nothing, and yet poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all things: troubled on every ſide, yet not diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, perplexed, but not in deſpair; alwayes bearing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in the body, the dying of the Lord Jeſus, that the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>x</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 11. 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> life alſo of Jeſus might be made manifeſt in their body, alwayes delivered unto death for Jeſus ſake, that the life alſo of Jeſus might be made manifeſt in their mortall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118019:13"/> fleſh. Are thoſe whom you call your Miniſters found ſuch, or do not thoſe whom they ſet you on, now to perſecute, appear ſuch as theſe and they the Contrary? Are they not plainly manifeſted by their fruits? Search, and ſee, how long will ye be deceived, and ſhut your Eyes againſt the noon day, and ſeek to ſupport ſuch as plainly appear not to be the Church of Chriſt, or the Minſters of his Glorious Goſpell; Whom the Lord, the Jealous God, is now come to pull up, being plants whom he hath not planted, and againſt whom his Sword is drawn, and fourbiſhed, by which both they that help, and they that are holpen, ſhall fall together: and ſhall not be put up, till the thoughts of his heart be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed; And how long will ye beat, tumult, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon, and cruelly intreat his witneſſes, whom from amongſt your ſelves he hath raiſed up to teſtifie againſt them, and to lead you out of the waies of deſtruction into the Paths of Peace, and out of dear love to your ſoules, preſſe through all hardſhips, and ſufferings, and difficulties at your hands, yea, theit lives are not dear to them for the finiſhing of their Teſtimony, and that your ſouls may be ſaved in this Powerfull day of the Lord Jeſus? will not theſe things be bitterneſſe in the end? What will you anſwer the Lord, whom ye thus requite for all his kindneſſe?</p>
            <p>Mind, and conſider: did not the Word of the Lord from the beginning, take hold on thoſe to whom it was ſent, though <note n="y" place="margin">Zach. 1. 5, 6.</note> the Fathers dyed, and the Prophets lived not for ever; and though they did put the <hi>z</hi> Evill day<note n="x" place="margin">Amos 6. 3.</note> far from them, and cauſed the Seat of Violence to come neer, and mocked at the Word of the Lord, and miſuſed his Meſſengers: Was there ever a Witneſs of God born againſt any thing, but the downfall thereof was at hand, according to the Witneſs, and aſſuredly came to paſſe, as they did abide Sufferings, who bore againſt it their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony; and the hotter the Sufferings, drew not the time the neerer? For as Jeſus Chriſt in his fleſh, on the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118019:14"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eph: 4. 8.</note> Croſſe, lead Captivity Captive, ſo tthrough Sufferings his Truth conquers, <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 2. 14, 15.</note> thorough death it overcomes him that hath the power of death, and <note n="c" place="margin">2 Colo. 15.</note> triumpheth over all and when the world ſeemeth to have upon it its greateſt Advantage, then is it aſcending on the Throne, and raigning over all.</p>
            <p>Turn a little over theſe later times, and obſerve calme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; When raged the Fire, and Faggot more furious againſt the Martyrs in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies, than when the hour was come, wherein that body of Popery which became ſo cruel, was to be extinguiſhed in this Nation? when were the Perſecutions of the Biſhops more fierce, then when the Parliament drew near, which pulled them up by Root, and Branch? What is become of that body of Popery in <hi>England</hi> to this Day? Where are the Biſhops, Deans, and Chapters, the Common Prayer, and thoſe heaps of Ceremoniall, and Superſtitious dead ſervices, and all that Hierarchy with the Appurtenances which had fortified it ſelf with ſuch lawes, and length of time, and mixed it ſelf ſo in, and with the Civill Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that as her Mother <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſhe ſaid, I have ſet my Neſt amongſt the ſtars, I ſit as a Queen and ſhall ſee no ſorrow, when loſſe of Children, and Widdow-hood came upon her in One day, fear, the ſnare, and the pit, and a horrible deſolation, even by the power that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported her? How contemptible and baſe, how much leſſe then things of naught, were the Martyrs in thoſe dayes accounted of, and the factious Puritanicall <hi>Non conformiſts,</hi> as they were then called? and how unlikely in the eyes of men; yea, how impoſſible a thing it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thoſe witneſſes, to turne the hand upon thoſe Generations, who in the height of their pride, ſcorn, and confidence, thought of nothing, but to ſwallow them up quick, and to root them out of the Land of the Living by the hand of Authority, which they had whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made their own, and the Lawes, and were ſtretching out their Armes ſo to do; Even when the <note n="d" place="margin">Jer. 4: 7.</note> Lyon came out of his Thicket, and the Fuller had laid his Axe to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118019:14"/> their Root and Branches. And when many of thoſe men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who, with others of their Brethren, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about thoſe Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> with the ſound of Rams Horns, (ſo deſpicable was the Witneſs to that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of men) before whom they fell, and in whoſe hearing (by it) was it ſaid, <hi>Curſed be the man before the Lord, that riſeth up, and buildeth this City Jericho, he ſhall lay the Foundation thereof in his Firſt-born; and in his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Son ſhall he ſet up the Gates of it;</hi> ſtrived ſo eagerly, and with vehemence to build it up again, as a City in <hi>Iſrael</hi> for them to dwell in, by the Name, and in the Rule of a coercive Presbytery, hating and deſpiſing the reſt of their Brethren, before whom <hi>Jericho</hi> fell, the witneſſes againſt them, as Heretiques, and Schiſmaticks, upon whom they made very ſharp ſteps, and joyned with the men of <hi>Jericho,</hi> the Common-enemy, to effect it: how laid they the Foundation thereof in the Synod their firſt-born, and ſet up their Gates in the youngeſt Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and little Catechiſme?</p>
            <p>By what ſtrange Overturnings, wonderful Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fearfull Deſolations, and ſtreames of the Blood of theſe Nations, hath the Lord (as of old) fulfilled the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his poor, contemned, and ſuffering Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, before the Eyes, and in the midſt of this Generation, beyond the Example of former times; in which, to be further particular, would be needleſs, and troubleſome, ſince with the Points of Steel, and in Letters of Blood, and Miſeries of Warre, they are freſhly engraven every where throughout theſe Dominions.</p>
            <p>And, yet, though there is to theſe things ſuch a Cloud of Witneſſes from the beginning, throughout all times on Record in Scripture, as aforeſaid; though ſince the Apoſtles dayes, Hiſtories have filled up of theſe things whole Volumnes, to the times of this Generation; Though in the ſight this Generation, and by their hands whole Multitudes have been deſtroyed, and carryed out
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118019:15"/> dead, who have oppoſed, and perſecuted the Witneſſes of Jeſus, beyond the Preſident of former times: And though the Feet of the Righteous Judgments of the Dreadful God, which carryed them out, are ſtanding at the door; yet do not the men of this Generation Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Fear before the Powerful God, and the words of his Holyneſs, uttered forth by the Spirit of Jeſus, who is riſen in this his Mighty Day, carrying forth his Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to teſtifie thereunto againſt all falſe Worſhips, and Deceit, and Vanities, and Cuſtoms of the World, and Deeds of Darkneſs, and Powers of Wickedneſſes, whom he brings forth as Signes and Wonders amongſt them, and makes living Teſtimonies for himſelf againſt them all.</p>
            <p>Who knowing the Terrour of the Lord: and his Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Day Approaching, wherein he will yet <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 1. 2. 26, 27.</note> once more ſhake not onely Earth, but the Heaven alſo; and in <note n="f" place="margin">Jude 14. 15.</note> Ten Thouſands of his Saints cometh to execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon all, and to convince all that are Ungodly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, of all their ungodly Deeds which they have ungod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ily committed, &amp; of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him, and with his mighty and ſtrong One, to render Vengeance with <note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 66. 15, 16. Eſa 28. 21. ane 29. 6.</note> Whirl-winds, Storms, and Tempeſts, and Thunder, and Earth-quakes, and great Noiſe and Flames of devouring Fire, upon the head of the wicked: Therefore do their <note n="h" place="margin">Jer. 23. 9.</note> Bones ſhake, and their Lips quiver, <note n="i" place="margin">Hab. 3. 16.</note> and their Bellies tremble, and their <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 16. 11.</note> Bowels ſound like a Harp, and their Eyes are like <hi>t</hi> Rivers of water, and their <note n="m" place="margin">Jer. 4. 19. and 9. 1.</note> hearts are<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 126.</note> pained, as it was with the Lords ſervants of Old, not cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to warn men, as in the ſight of God, to know the hour of their Viſitation, that ſo they may be hid in the day of the Lords fierce Anger, which verily is coming on the Inhabitants of the Earth: In requital of which, and their love therein, they are mocked, and ſcorned, and reviled, and reproached, and beat, and tumulted, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, and cruelly ſcourged, and ſome of their Blood
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118019:15"/> drawn, and ſome of their lives taken away, and thought not fit to live upon the Earth, as was Jeſus Chriſt, and his Witneſſes, ſince the Foundation of the world.</p>
            <p>Do ye thus requite the Lord, O ye fooliſh People, and unwiſe! What will ye do in the day of Viſitation? where then will ye flee, and where will you leave your glory? Hear ye, and give ear, be not proud, for the Lord hath ſpoken: Give glory to the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cauſe darkneſs, and before your feet ſtumble on the dark Mountains; and whileſt ye look for light, he<note n="n" place="margin">Jer. 23: 16:</note> turn it into the ſhadow of Death, and make it groſſe Darkneſs; for verily it haſtens on this Generation: But if you will not hear, Our ſoules ſhall weep for you in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places for your Pride, and Our Eyes ſhall weep ſore, and run down with Tears, becauſe you will not know in this your day, the things that belong unto your Peace.</p>
            <p>And thus have I diſcharged my Conſcience unto you, as in the ſight of God, whether you will hear, or whether you will forbear, which you ſhall one day remember whether you will, or no, in the day when the Book of Conſcience ſhall be opened, and wherein God ſhall judge all men by the Man Jeſus Chriſt, whom in our meaſure we witneſs, and you perſecute.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Behold a Whirle-wind of the Lord is gone forth in fury, even a grievous Whirle-wind, it ſhall fall grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly on the head of the Wicked, the Anger of the Lord ſhall not return untill he hath executed, untill he hath performed the thoughts of his heart; in the latter dayes, ye ſhall conſider it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <!-- Jeremiah 23:19,20 -->
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:118019:16"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>LIne 16. read entertainment, for enterraynment.</p>
            <p>Pag. 4. line 33. read been, for have. P. 7. l. 27. r. water for ter. P. 8. l. 17. r. and,<note place="margin">Title Page. Book.</note> for or. P. 9. l. 9. add (o) Synagogues; and (p) 17. 1. 2. 10. for 17. 12. 10. Margent. l. 16. r. And did he not bid them go, for, and they bad him to go. P. 34. r. the, for their. p. 10. l. 13. Add Heb. 11. 4. Margent. p. 11. l. 21. r. Amon, for Hamon; add (i) over Amon. p. 12. l. 15. add (x) over Ier. 6. 10. Margent. p. 16. l. 4. add Heb. 11. 16. Margent. p. 17. l. 33. add the, after of. p. 18. l. 28. blot out were. p. 20. l. 19. r. it, for that. p. 23 .l. 3. r. Habitation, for Haitation. l. 14. r. where, for when. p. 26. l. 14. blot out by. p. 27. l. 34. add of, before this. p. 29. l. 22. r. meaſures, for meaſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:118019:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118019:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Friends,</hi> By reaſon of the Authors abſence; and the extraordinary haſte of giving forth the ſubject in hand, ſome Errors have eſcaped in Printing, which you are deſired thus to obſerve, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>LIne 16. read entertainment, for enterraynment.<note place="margin">Title Page. Book.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 4. line 33. read been, for have. P. 7. l. 27. r. water for ter. P. 8 l. 17. r. and, for or. P. 9. l. 9. add (o) Synagog es; and (p) 17. 1. 2. 10. for 17. 12. 10. Margent. l. 16. r. And did he not bid them go, for, and they bad him to go. P. 34. r. the, for their. p. 10. l. 13. Add Heb. 11. 4. Margent. p. 11. l. 21. r. Amon, for Hamon; add (i) over Amon. p. 12. l. 15. add (x) over Ier. 6. 10. Margent. p. 16. l. 4. add Heb 11. 16. Margent. p. 17. l. 33. add the, after of. p. 18. l. 28. blot out were. p. 20. l. 19. r. it, for that. p. 23 .l. 3. r. Habitation, for Haitation. l. 14. r. where, for when. p. 26. l. 14. blot out by. p. 27. l. 34. add of, before this. p. 29. l. 22. r. meaſures, for meaſure.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
